Joe: Individuals with autism
typically struggle with fully
engaging in conversations.
They may interrupt the person
talking or decide the conversation
is over and walk away while the
other person is still speaking.
They can suffer from Social imagination
difficulties by not having the
ability to imagine what another
person may be feeling, thinking
or experiencing and therefore lack
the ability to relate to others.
They may have trouble with eye contact
which is important for communicating
interest in having a social interaction
with someone, and this difficulty
can often be misconstrued by others
as disinterest or inattention.
To individuals with autism social
interactions can appear unnatural and very
stressful so many may try to avoid them.
They suffer from social inhibition,
consciously or subconsciously
avoiding social interaction
because of the possibility of
disapproving reactions from others.
It can be difficult for individuals
with autism to make or keep friends and
they may say they don't need or want
friends and isolate themselves socially.
They may have less interest in social
interaction for its own sake and be
more interested in things than in
people, and are often content when left
alone to pursue their own interests
Some choose to be social, however
their issues in social understanding
and empathy can prevent them from
smoothly engaging with others.
An individual may know they are supposed
to use words to start a conversation
with others however, they may not
know quite how to use them, and may
end up having life-long difficulty
navigating through social situations.